Register of the John A. Dolan papers
Hoover Institution Archives
John A. Dolan papers
1919-1923
56021
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, and minutes relating to Allied administration of occupied territories, relief operations, labor relations, enforcement of laws and ordinances, and complaints made against Allied occupation troops in the Rhineland.
Dolan, John A.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1956.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
John A. Dolan supervised the Child Feeding Relief Efforts in Germany following World War I. He continued his stay in Koblenz, occupying the position of District Executive for the American Department of the Inter-Allied Rhineland High Commission from 1920 to 1922, at which time the operations were transferred from the Americans to the French.
Scope and Content of Collection
The John A. Dolan papers are comprised of printed matter, correspondence, personnel papers, meeting minutes, reports, and ordinances regarding the post-World War I Inter-Allied Rhineland High Commission. The commission was established to assist post-war Germany in its recovery and to supervise the activies of the country.
Inter-Allied Rhineland High Commission.; Germany--History--Allied occupation, 1918-1930.; Military government.; Rhineland (Germany)
- American Friends Service Committee File, 1920-1923
  Scope and Contents note
  The American Friends Service Committee began its work in the early 1920s and worked to feed hundreds of German children in various cities following World War I. The series is comprised of correspondence, memoranda and statistical reports relating to the committee's relief work.
  - Correspondence, 1920-1923 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Reports, circa 1920 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- The Board of Conciliation File, 1920-1922
  The Board of Conciliation was appointed by the Inter-Allied Rhineland High Commission to arbitrate disputes. The series is composed of meeting minutes, correspondence, and reports.
  - Brohltal railroad, 1922 April (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Koblenz street car strike, 1920-1921 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Concordia Hutte, 1922 March (Box-folder 1: 5)
- Correspondence, 1920-1923 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  Correspondence discussing official business, occupied territories, drivers licenses, and thanks for service. Correspondants include: John A. Dolan, the German Commissioner for the Occupied Rhineland Territories, the President of the Inter-allied Rhineland High Commission, the Secretary of State, Dr. Brandt, and Henry T. Allen.
- Crimes committed by soldiers, 1919-1922 (Box-folder 1: 7)
- Financial records, 1920-1922 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  Financial information pertaining to the aftermath of World War I, including costs of war, reparations determined at the Paris Conference and the Cannes Conference, fluctuations of the German mark, and costs of the Inter-Allied Rhineland High Commission.
- Intelligence Committee meetings, c. 1920 (Box-folder 1: 9-11, 2: 1-3)
  Contains meeting minutes, correspondence, memoranda, reports, and draft ordinances.
- Meeting minutes, circa 1920 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  Discussing issues such as strikes, distribution of materials, and wages.
- Ordinances, circa 1920 (Box-folder 2: 5)
- Personnel papers, circa 1920 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  Documents about Inter-Allied Rhineland High Commission employees, including recommendation letters, thanks for service, short biographies, statements of grief, and an address to the Graduating Class of General and Commercial School A.F.G.
- Printed matter, 1920-1923 (Box-folder 2: 7)
- Reports, 1921-1923 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  Includes brief descriptions of the Commission and its purposes, explanations of representative duties, monthly reports, and information regarding the ongoings of occupied territories.
- DECLASSIFIED U.S. GOVERNMENT RECORDS, 1922
  Includes correspondence and map regarding the A.R.A - US Navy communcation system in Europe.
  - 2016 May release of records, 1922 (Box-folder : 2: 9)